<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Users_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="AdministeringVMs">
<title>Managing Virtual Machines</title>

<section id="CreatingVMs">
<title>Creating Virtual Machines</title>
<para>
To create a Virtual Machine (VM) using the dashboard, you need to have 
already logged into the 
dashboard and created your private key, as explained before.
</para>

<para>
To create a VM, the steps are as follows:
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Number of virtual CPU cores (VCPUs)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Amount of memory</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Disk space</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
On the left hand menu, select the Project that must be used for this VM.
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
Go to <menuchoice><guimenu>Instances</guimenu></menuchoice> on the left hand 
menu. This will display a list of VMs currently running in your project.
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Launch Instance</guimenu></menuchoice> on the 
top right hand side of the dashboard. A new menu appears where you can enter:
</para>


<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
<menuchoice><guimenu>Instance name</guimenu></menuchoice> is the name of the 
machine you want to create. Please note that this name will not be registered 
in the DNS
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<menuchoice><guimenu>Flavor</guimenu></menuchoice> is the size of the machine 
you want to create. These are specified using VPCU (number of virtual CPUs, 
GB of disk space for the system disk, MB RAM for the memory). Selecting small 
flavors is more economical and the flavor of a virtual machine can be changed 
later if required.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
As <menuchoice><guimenu>Instance Boot Source</guimenu></menuchoice> 
select <menuchoice><guimenu>Boot from Image</guimenu></menuchoice> or 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Boot from Snapshot</guimenu></menuchoice> and then 
specify its name
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>
Switch the tab for 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu></menuchoice> 
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Select the keypair you created. This will allow you to log in as root using 
the key
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
You can also specify the admin (usually root) password of the instance. 
Please note that this is not guaranteed to always work (the image can't 
support the “injection” of this password). It is therefore suggested to use 
the ssh-key mechanisms.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Specify the Security group to be used for this VM (security groups are 
discussed in <xref linkend="SecurityGroups"/>).
</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>
Swith the tab for <menuchoice><guimenu>Networking</guimenu></menuchoice>.
You should see one network called <replaceable>&lt;ProjectName&gt;-lan
</replaceable>, and in 
some cases also another network called 
<replaceable>&lt;ProjectName&gt;-wan</replaceable>.
Select the former one if your VM doesn't need to be visible on the Internet. 
Select instead the <replaceable>&lt;ProjectName&gt;-wan</replaceable>  
network if your VM must have a public IP.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Launch</guimenu></menuchoice> to start the 
virtual machine being created. When this returns to the overview screen, 
there will be a line with the instance name, ip adress and status. The status 
should be active once the install is complete.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

<para>
Once the status of the machine is 'Active', you can watch the console to see 
it installing and booting. On the right hand side of the table, under 
<menuchoice><guimenu>More</guimenu></menuchoice>, there is a pull down menu. 
Options include <menuchoice><guimenu>View Log</guimenu></menuchoice> and 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Console</guimenu></menuchoice>. For a Linux machine, 
select <menuchoice><guimenu>Console</guimenu></menuchoice> to access to the 
console of the VM.
</para>


<warning><para>
Please note that Virtual Machines instantiated on the Cloud aren't
registered in the DNS. This means that you'll have to refer to them
using their IP numbers.
</para></warning>

<note><para>
Please note that this setting the admin password is not guaranteed to always 
work (the image can't support the “injection” of this password). It is 
therefore suggested to use the ssh-key mechanisms. 
</para></note>

</section>

<section id="AccessingVMs">
<title>Accessing to VMs</title>
<para>
Assuming you created a Linux virtual machine, using the keypair provided on 
the start of the VM creation, you can now log in as root.

Assuming you stored your <replaceable>my_key</replaceable> keypair in 
<replaceable>~/private</replaceable>:
</para>

<screen>
$ ssh -o GSSAPIAuthentication=no -i ~/my_key root@10.62.15.3
</screen>

<para>
<warning><para>
Please note that VMs of the Cloud are not registered in the DNS, and therefore you must use the IP address.
</para></warning>
</para>

</section>


<section id="NetworkCond">
<title>Network considerations</title>
<para>
VMs created using the <replaceable>xyz-lan</replaceable> network are
“visible” from both the LAN of Padova and Legnaro. This means that e.g.
you can access via ssh a VM of the Cloud directly from your desktop located
in Padova or Legnaro. Security groups (discussed below) and firewalls
set on the VM (e.g. through iptables) then determine which services/port can
be accessed.
</para>
<para>
The contrary is instead not possible: from a VM created using the
<replaceable>xyz-lan</replaceable> network it is generally not possible to
access a host/service hosted in Padova or Legnaro LANs. It is instead
possible to access the outside Internet network.
</para>
</section>


<section id="AllocatingFloating">
<title>Allocating a public (floating) IP address to an instance</title>
<para>
When an instance is created in OpenStack, it is automatically assigned a 
fixed IP address.
If a VM needs to be visible on the Internet, in addition to the fixed IP 
address a public (floating) IP address must be attached to the instance.
Floating IP addresses can have their associations modified at any time, 
regardless of the state of the instances involved. 

</para>

<para>
To assign a floating IP to a VM, first of all create the VM
as described in <xref linkend="CreatingVMs"/>, 
using the <replaceable>&lt;ProjectName&gt;-wan</replaceable> network.
The following procedure then details the reservation of a floating IP address 
from an existing pool of public addresses and the association of that 
address with a specific instance.

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
From the dashboard click 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu></menuchoice>.
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
Click the <menuchoice><guimenu>Floating IPs</guimenu></menuchoice> tab, 
which shows the floating IP addresses allocated to instances.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Allocate IP to Project</guimenu></menuchoice>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> 
Choose <replaceable>Ext</replaceable> as the pool from which to pick the 
IP address and click <menuchoice><guimenu>Allocate IP</guimenu></menuchoice>. 
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> 
In the <menuchoice><guimenu>Manage Floating IP 
Associations</guimenu></menuchoice> dialog box, choose the following options:

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para> 
The <menuchoice><guimenu>IP Address</guimenu></menuchoice> field is filled 
automatically, but you can add a new IP address by clicking the + button
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
In the <menuchoice><guimenu>Ports to be associated</guimenu></menuchoice> 
field, select a port from the list (the list shows all the instances with 
their fixed IP addresses).
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
Click  <menuchoice><guimenu>Associate</guimenu></menuchoice>.
</para></listitem>


</itemizedlist>


</para>


<para>
To disassociate an IP address from an instance, click the 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Disassociate</guimenu></menuchoice> button.
</para>

<para>
To release the floating IP address back into the pool of addresses, 
click the <menuchoice><guimenu>More</guimenu></menuchoice> button 
and select the <menuchoice><guimenu>Release Floating IP</guimenu></menuchoice>
option.
</para>


</section>

<section id="Flavors">
<title>Flavors</title>
<para>
Flavors define the virtual machine size such as:
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Number of virtual CPU cores (VCPUs)</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Amount of memory</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Disk space</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
When an instance has to be created, the flavor to be used for this VM must
be chosen. Information about the flavors can be seen in the
<menuchoice><guimenu>Flavor Details</guimenu></menuchoice> box in the
Dashboard.
</para>

<note><para>
For what concerns VCPUs, please note that the Cloud middleware is configured
to allow some “overbooking”. The Cloud Area Padovana is configured so that a
physical core is mapped to 4 VCPUs
</para></note>

<para>
A disk size of 0 means that the size of the disk is the same as that in the
image. For other cases, it may be necessary to resize the partitions.
</para>
<para>
If you find that the specific flavor you require is not available, please
contact <email>cloud-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>.
</para>


</section>


<section id="SecurityGroups">
<title>Security Groups</title>
<para>
Security groups are sets of IP filter rules that define networking access and 
are applied to all instances within a project using that group. As
described in <xref linkend="CreatingVMs"/>, 
when you create an instance you have to specify
the security group to be used.
</para>

<para>
To set such IP rules, users can either add rules to the default security group 
or can add a new security group with the desided rules.
</para>

<para>
For example the following procedure enables SSH and ICMP (ping) access to 
instances using the default security group. The rules apply to all instances 
within a given project using this security group, and should be set 
(just once) for every 
project unless there is a reason to prohibit SSH or ICMP access to the 
instances.

This procedure can be adjusted as necessary to add additional security group 
rules to a project, if needed.
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
Log in to the dashboard, choose a project, and click 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Access &amp; Security</guimenu></menuchoice>. The 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Security Groups</guimenu></menuchoice> tab shows the security 
groups that are available for this project.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Select the <menuchoice><guimenu>default</guimenu></menuchoice> 
security group and click <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit Rules</guimenu></menuchoice>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
To allow SSH access, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Add Rule</guimenu></menuchoice>.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para> 
In the Add Rule dialog box, enter the following values:

<informaltable frame="all">
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
    <row><entry>Rule</entry><entry>SSH</entry></row>
    <row><entry>Remote</entry><entry>CIDR</entry></row>
    <row><entry>CIDR</entry><entry>0.0.0.0/0</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>



<note><para>
To accept requests from a particular range of IP addresses, specify the IP address block in 
the <menuchoice><guimenu>CIDR</guimenu></menuchoice> box.
</para></note>

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Add.</guimenu></menuchoice>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
To add an ICMP rule, click <menuchoice><guimenu>Add Rule</guimenu></menuchoice>.
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
In the Add Rule dialog box, enter the following values:


<informaltable>
<tgroup cols="2">
<tbody>
    <row><entry>Rule</entry><entry>All ICMP</entry></row>
    <row><entry>Direction</entry><entry>Ingress</entry></row>
    <row><entry>Remote</entry><entry>CIDR</entry></row>
    <row><entry>CIDR</entry><entry>0.0.0.0/0</entry></row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>


</para></listitem> 

<listitem><para>
Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Add.</guimenu></menuchoice>
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</para>

<note><para>
If you need to enable some services on a Virtual Machine, besides setting the
specific IP rules through security groups, be sure that the relevant ports are 
also enabled (e.g. via iptables) on the Virtual Machine.
</para></note>


</section>

<section id="StoppingAndStartingVMs">
<title>Stopping and Starting VMs</title>

<para>
VMs can be stopped and started in different ways, available in the Dashboad 
menu (<menuchoice><guimenu>Instances</guimenu><guisubmenu>More</guisubmenu></menuchoice>).
</para>

<para>
The cleanest way to shutdown (or reboot) an instance is to log on the VM and 
issue from the shell the shutdown/reboot command. In fact if the 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Soft Reboot</guimenu></menuchoice> 
or <menuchoice><guimenu>Hard Reboot</guimenu></menuchoice> or 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Shutdown</guimenu></menuchoice> actions are chosen, 
there could be problems with networking when the VM is later restarted.
</para>

<para>
<menuchoice><guimenu>Pause</guimenu></menuchoice>/<menuchoice><guimenu>Unpause</guimenu></menuchoice> 
allows for temporary suspension of the VM. The VM is kept in 
memory but it is not allocated any CPU time.
</para>

<para>
<menuchoice><guimenu>Suspend</guimenu></menuchoice>/<menuchoice><guimenu>Resume</guimenu></menuchoice> 
stores the VM onto disk and recovers it later. This is faster 
than stop/start and the VM returns to the place is was when the suspend was 
performed rather than a new boot cycle.
</para>

</section>

<section id="Contextualisation">
<title>Contextualisation</title>
<para>
Contextualisation is the process to configure a virtual machine after it has been 
installed. Typical examples would be to create additional users, install software 
packages or call a configuration management system. These steps can be used to 
take a reference image and customise it further. Contextualisation is only run 
once when the VM is created
</para>

<para>
The public images provided in the Cloud Area Padovana include a contextualisation 
feature using the open source <literal>cloud-init</literal> package.
</para>

<para>
With cloud-init, data to be used for contextualisation are called 
<literal>user data</literal>.

To launch instances with user data using the OpenStack dashboard,
you can fill in the 
<menuchoice><guimenu>user data</guimenu></menuchoice> tab.

Using the Openstack command line tool, the <literal>--user_data</literal>
option of the <command>nova boot</command> command must be used, e.g.:

<screen>
nova boot my_vm --image "SL65-Padova-x86_64-20141023-QCOW2" --flavor m1.xsmall --user_data my_data.txt --key_name my_key
</screen>
</para>


<para>
For example to run a command during contextualisation, the <literal>#cloud-config</literal> directive
can be used:

<screen>
cat > cern-config-users.txt &lt;&lt; EOF
#cloud-config
runcmd:
 - [ /usr/bin/yum, "install", -y, "cern-config-users" ]
 - [ /usr/sbin/cern-config-users, --setup-all ]
EOF
</screen>

</para>

<para>
User data can be provided as a gzip file if needed where the user data is larger than 16384 bytes, 
e.g.:

<screen>
cat > userdata4zip.txt &lt;&lt;EOF
#!/bin/sh
wget -O /tmp/geolist.txt http://frontier.cern.ch/geolist.txt
EOF
gzip -c userdata4zip.txt > userdata4zip.gz

nova boot my_server --image "SL65-Padova-x86_64-20141023-QCOW2" --flavor m1.xsmall \
--user_data userdata4zip.gz --key_name my_key
</screen>

</para>

<para>
With the <literal>#include</literal> or <literal>Content-Type: text/x-include-url</literal>
directives, it is possible to specify a list of urls, one url per line. The userdata passed by the 
urls can be plain txt, gzip file or mime-multi-part script. E.g.:

<screen>
cat userdata.txt &lt;&lt;EOF
#! /bin/bash
wget -O /tmp/robots.txt http://www.ubuntu.com/robots.txt
EOF

cat > userdata4include.txt &lt;&lt;EOF
#include
# entries are one url per line. comment lines beginning with '#' are allowed
# urls are passed to urllib.urlopen, so the format must be supported there
http://frontier.cern.ch/userdata.txt
EOF
</screen>

</para>

<para>
cloud-init supply also a method called "multiple part" to supply user data in multiple ways, 
which means you can use userdata script and cloud-config (or other methods recognized by cloud-init) 
at the same time. cloud-init provides a script write-mime-multipart to generate a final userdata 
file. Here is an example:

<screen>
cat > userdata4script &lt;&lt;EOF
#! /bin/bash
mkdir -p /tmp/rdu
echo "Hello World!" > helloworld.txt
EOF
 
cat userdata4config
#cloud-config
runcmd:
 - [ wget, "http://slashdot.org", -O, /tmp/index.html ]
 
cat userdata4include
#include
# entries are one url per line. comment lines beginning with '#' are allowed
# urls are passed to urllib.urlopen, so the format must be supported there
http://frontier.cern.ch/userdata.txt
</screen>


Then use <command>write-mime-multipart</command> to generate 
<replaceable>userdata4multi.txt</replaceable> and use it to launch an instance:

<screen>
write-mime-multipart -o userdata4multi.txt userdata4script userdata4config userdata4inc

nova boot my_server --image "SL65-Padova-x86_64-20141023-QCOW2" --flavor m1.xsmall \
--user_data userdata4multi.txt --key_name my_key
</screen>


</para>


<para>
On Internet a lot of documentation (along with examples) is available on
cloud-init, such as in the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/community/CloudInit">Ubuntu 
Documentation</ulink>.
</para>


</section>

<section id="ResizingVMs">
<title>Resizing VMs</title>

<para>
If the size of a virtual machine needs to be changed, such as adding more 
memory or cores, this can be done using the resize operations. Using resize, 
you can select a new flavor for your virtual machine. The operation will 
reboot the virtual machine and will take several minutes of downtime, so this 
operation should be scheduled as it will lead to application downtime.
</para>

<para>
To resize a VM using the Horizon graphical Interface:
</para>

<para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>Select the <menuchoice><guimenu>Instances</guimenu></menuchoice> 
menu and the <menuchoice><guimenu>Resize Instance</guimenu></menuchoice> 
option on the actions</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>After the new flavor has been selected, the status will 
become 'resize' or 'migrating'</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>The status will change after several minutes to 'Confirm' or 
'Revert Resize/Migrate'. You may need to refresh the web browser page to 
reflect the new status.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>Select <menuchoice><guimenu>Confirm Resize/Migrate</guimenu></menuchoice> 
if you wish to change the instance to the new configuration.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
The status will then change to 'Active' once completed.
</para>

</section>


<section id="SnapshottingVMs">
<title>Snapshotting VMs</title>

<para>
It is possible to create a snapshot of a VM, and then the saved snapshot can 
be used to start new instance(s).
</para>

<para>
The new instance can also have a flavor different (but not smaller for what 
concern the disk size) than the source VM. It is therefore suggested to use 
the smallest (in terms of disk) possible flavor for the source VM (for SL6.x 
related images this is 'm1.xsmall').
</para>

<para>
Before doing a snapshot, it is needed to clean the network configurations of 
the “source” VM. For SL6.x related OS this can be done using the following instructions, once logged as root on the “source” VM:
</para>

<screen>
/bin/rm /etc/udev/rules.d/70-persistent-net.rules
/bin/rm /lib/udev/write_net_rules
</screen>

<para>
Before doing the snapshot (that can be done using the web-based dashboard, it 
is recommended to shut down the source VM to make sure that all data is 
flushed to disk. To perform this shutdown of the VM, please don't do it 
through Openstack. Instead please do the shutdown within the VM (i.e. log as root to the VM and issue <command>shutdown -h now</command> or 
<command>poweroff</command>).
</para>

<warning><para>
In the production Cloud it is possible to save in the Image service
only snapshots with a maximum size of 25 GB. 
</para></warning>


</section>


<section id="DeletingVMs">
<title>Deleting VMs</title>

<para>
VMs can be deleted using the <menuchoice><guimenu>Terminate Instance</guimenu></menuchoice> 
option in the OpenStack dashboard.
</para>

<warning><para>
Note: This will immediately terminate the instance, delete all content of the 
virtual machine and erase the ephemeral disk. This operation is not 
recoverable.
</para></warning>

</section>

</chapter>

