<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Users_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="ManagingStorage">
<title>Managing Storage</title>

<para>
There are several ways of handling disk storage in the Cloud Area Padovana:
</para>

<para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
<literal>Ephemeral storage</literal> exists only for the life of a virtual machine 
instance. It 
will persist across reboots of the guest operating system but when the 
instance is deleted so is the associated storage. The size of the ephemeral 
storage is defined in the virtual machine flavor.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
<literal>Volumes</literal> are persistent virtualized block devices independent of any 
particular instance. Volumes may be attached to a single instance at a time, 
but may be detached or reattached to a different instance while retaining 
all data, much like a USB drive. The size of the volume can be selected when 
it is created within the quota limits for the particular project.
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</para>

<section id="EphemeralStorage">
<title>Ephemeral storage</title>

<para>
Ephemeral storage exists only for the life of a virtual machine instance. 
It will persist across reboots of the guest operating system but when the 
instance is deleted so is the associated storage. The size of the ephemeral 
storage is defined in the virtual machine flavor.
</para>

<para>
Among the flavor details (that are listed in the Dashboard when a VM has to 
be launched or can be seen using the <command>nova flavor-list</command> 
command), there is an attribute called 'Ephemeral'. When you use a flavor 
with an ephemeral disk size different from zero, the instance is booted with 
an extra virtual disk whose size is indicated by the ephemeral value. 
This ephemeral disk can be useful where you want to partition the second disk 
or have a specific disk configuration which is not possible within the system 
disk configuration.
</para>

<warning><para>
Please note that backups are not performed on ephemeral storage systems.
</para></warning>
</section>

<section id="Volumes">
<title>Volumes</title>

<para>
Volumes are persistent virtualized block devices independent of any 
particular instance. Volumes may be attached to a single instance at a time 
(i.e. not like a distributed filesystem such as Lustre or Gluster), but they 
may be detached or reattached to a different instance while retaining all 
data, much like a USB drive.
</para>

<para>
The steps to add a Volume are:
</para>

<para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
Define a disk volume of the size required (12GB in example 
below) with the volume name defined (<replaceable>testvol</replaceable> in the 
example below). Using the Dashboard, click on 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Volumes</guimenu></menuchoice> and then 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Create Volume</guimenu></menuchoice>. 
In the “Create Volume” window specify the name of the volume and the desired size.
As <menuchoice><guimenu>Volume Source</guimenu></menuchoice> specify “No source, empty volume”. 

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="./images/CreateVolumeCinder.jpg" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="./images/testvolCreation.jpg" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
The new defined volume will appear in the 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Volumes</guimenu></menuchoice> tab. To attach this volume to an 
existing instance, click on 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit attachments</guimenu></menuchoice> and select the 
relevant Virtual Machine.

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="./images/AttachVolumeToInstance.jpg" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="./images/AttachVolumeToInstance1.jpg" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>

</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
Log in to the instance and check if the disk has been added:
</para>

<screen>
grep vdb /proc/partitions
 252       48   12582912 vdb
</screen>

<para>
If needed, create a file system on it (this will scratch the disk !):
</para>

<screen>
mkfs -t ext4 /dev/vdb
</screen>

<para>
Mount the volume:
</para>

<screen>
mount /dev/sdb /mnt
</screen>


<para>
To detach a volume from an instance, first of all log into the virtual 
machine that has the volume mounted, and unmount it:
</para>

<screen>
umount /mnt
</screen>

<para>
Then, using the Dashboard, click on 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Volumes</guimenu></menuchoice>, click on 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Edit attachments</guimenu></menuchoice> for the relevant 
volume and select <menuchoice><guimenu>Detach Volume</guimenu></menuchoice>. 
The detached volume can then be associated to another VM, as described above 
(you won't have to re-create the file system, otherwise you will lose the 
content of the volume !)
</para>

<para>
If a volume is not needed any longer, to completely remove it (note that 
this step cannot be reverted!):
</para>

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para>
if needed, detach the volume from the associated instance
</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>
using the Dashboard, click on 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Volumes</guimenu></menuchoice>, select the relevant 
volume and then select 
<menuchoice><guimenu>Delete Volumes</guimenu></menuchoice>
</para></listitem>

</itemizedlist>


<warning><para>
Please note that backups are not performed on volumes.
</para></warning>

<section id="SharingVolume">
<title>Sharing a volume between multiple (virtual) machines </title>
<para>
Follow the creation and the format of cinder persistent volume above.
</para>
<para>
Create the mount point and mount the volume:
<screen>
mkdir /dataNfs
mount /dev/sdb /dataNfs
</screen>
</para>
<para>
Ensure in your virtual machine designed for nfs server are present the follow rpms and their dependencies:
<screen>
nfs-utils
nfs-utils-lib
rpcbind
</screen>
</para>
<para>
Insert the corret export in /etc/exports file. For example for all the virtual machine in the same subnet 10.62.15.* (check the subnet with ifconfig command) the contents of the /etc/exports file shoud be:
<screen>
/dataNfs 10.62.15.*(async,rw,no_root_squash)
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Check the iptables on the virtual machine. In the file /etc/sysconfig/iptables ensure other virtaula machines could access to porst 111, 2049, 875 UPD and TPC. So your file /etc/sysconfig/iptables should be like this:
<screen>
*filter
:INPUT ACCEPT [0:0]
:FORWARD ACCEPT [0:0]
:OUTPUT ACCEPT [0:0]
-A INPUT -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -p icmp -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -i lo -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m tcp -p tcp --dport 22 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m tcp -p tcp --dport 111 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m udp -p udp --dport 111 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m tcp -p tcp --dport 875 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m udp -p udp --dport 875 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m tcp -p tcp --dport 2049 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -m state --state NEW -m udp -p udp --dport 2049 -j ACCEPT
-A INPUT -j REJECT --reject-with icmp-host-prohibited
-A FORWARD -j REJECT --reject-with icmp-host-prohibited
COMMIT
</screen>
Remember to restart iptables after any change on that file:
<screen>
/etc/init.d/iptables restart
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Check the Access &amp; Security of your tenat and remember to add th rule Ingress IPv4 TCP and UDP for the ports 111 875 and 2049. Like the image below:
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
  <imagedata fileref="./images/AccessAndSecurity.jpg"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</para>

<para>
Restart nfs server:
<screen>
/etc/init.d/nfs restart
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Enter in another instance of the same tentant and mount via nfs filesystem like example below (if some errors occurs check you have installed rpcbind):
<screen>
mount -t nfs 10.62.15.4:/dataNfs /mnt
</screen>
</para>


</section>
</section>


<section id="AccessingExternalStorage">
<title>Accessing storage external to the Cloud</title>

<para>
TBD
</para>

</section>

</chapter>
