<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Users_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="Overview">
<title>Overview of the CloudVeneto</title>
<para>                                                                          
The <literal>CloudVeneto</literal> is an OpenStack based cloud.         
</para>

<para>
It implements a IaaS (Infrastructure as a service):
it allows the instantiation of Virtual Machines (VMs) of the desired
environments (in terms of operating system, installed software, etc.)
and of the desired flavors (in terms of processors, memory size, etc.).
</para>


<para>                                                                          
Even if it is a single, logical Cloud service, its resources are spread in various  
different locations: CSIA Padova, INFN Padova and INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Legnaro (LNL). 

</para>

<para>                                                                          
The CloudVeneto is currently based on the Icehouse version of the    
OpenStack middleware.                     
</para>


<section id="Projects">
<title>Projects</title>
<para>
<literal>Projects</literal> (also known as tenants)                             
are organizational units in the cloud. A project is used to map or isolate users 
and their resources. </para>

<para>                                                                             
Projects are given quotas on resource usage, in terms of virtual machines, cores,  
memory, storage, etc.                                                              
</para>

<para>                                                                             
A project can have a single user as member (personal project) but the typical use  
case are shared projects, with multiple users as members, which can map to experiments,                                                          organizations, research groups, etc.                                               
A user can be on multiple projects at the same time and switch between them.       
</para>


<para>
In the CloudVeneto projects usually map to experiments or other research 
groups. Among the project's users there is a team leader who is responsible to manage
(accepting or refusing) membership requests for the project.                       
</para>

<!-- para>                                                                             
A special shared project, called <literal>guest</literal> is used for all other    
users: it has a small quota to allow testing the Cloud infrastructure.             
</para -->

<warning><para>                                                                
<literal>Personal private</literal> projects are instead discouraged and are created only for 
convincing  reasons.     
</para></warning>
</section>


<section id="NetworkAccess">

<title>Network access</title>
<para>                                                                         
Access to Virtual Machines created in the CloudVeneto depends on your affiliation.

<itemizedlist>

<listitem><para><literal>INFN users:</literal></para>
<para>
VM are by default “visible” from the Local Area Networks (LANs) of both Padova and 
LNL. This means that e.g. users can access via ssh VMs of the Cloud directly 
from their desktops located in Padova or Legnaro. 

It is then possible to control which services/ports can be accessed
using the security groups (discussed later) and firewalls
on the relevant VMs.
</para>

<para>
If it is necessary to log on a VM of the Cloud from the Internet, it is 
necessary to go through a gate machine. For this purpose users can rely
on the existing gate hosts in Padova and Legnaro. 
Users who don't have an account on such gate hosts can rely on 
a Cloud specific gate host (<literal>cld-gate.pd.infn.it</literal>): please contact 
<email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email> if you need an account on such 
machine.
</para>

<para>
If needed, e.g. if a VM should host a service accessible from the 
Internet, such VM on the Cloud can be given a public IP.
If this is the case please contact 
<email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>. 
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><literal>UNIPD users:</literal></para>
<para>
VM may be accessed from a gate (<literal>cld-blu-gate.cedc.csia.unipd.it</literal>): please contact
<email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email> if you need an account on such
machine.
</para>
<para>
If needed, e.g. if a VM should host a service accessible from the 
Internet, such VM on the Cloud can be given a public IP.
If this is the case please contact 
<email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>. 
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para><literal>"external" users:</literal></para>
<para>Please contact <email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>
</para>
</listitem>

</itemizedlist>
</para>

<para>
From a VM of the Cloud, it is possible to access the Internet, while by default
it is not possible to access a host/service hosted in Padova or Legnaro. 
If, for some reasons, you need to access some
services hosted in Padova or Legnaro from the Cloud, please contact
<email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>.
</para>

</section>


<section id="GettingHelp">
<title>Getting help</title>
<para>                                                                             
If you have problems using the CloudVeneto cloud, please 
contact the admins at <email>cedc-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>.
</para>

<warning>
<para>
Disclaimer: technical support on the CloudVeneto platform is provided on <literal>best effort</literal> basis.
The CloudVeneto provide and infrastructure where you can instantiate your servers but, once activated, your
server are <literal>managed by you</literal>.
</para>

<para>This implies that the support crew <literal>don't provide support</literal> on topics like:</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>How to install/compile/configure your software;</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ssh / scp basic usage (ask your Department / Institution technicians about that);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Basic linux usage (except what's described in this guide);</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Accessing your VM 'the graphical way'.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</warning>

<para>                                                                             
Changes and planned interventions to the service will be posted on the             
<email>cloud-users@pd.infn.it</email>.                                       
All registered users to the Cloud are member of this mailing list.    
</para>
</section>


<section id="GivingCredit">
<title>Acknowledge CloudVeneto / Scientific citations</title>
<para>    
If you wish to give credit for the use of the CloudVeneto infrastructure in your scientific publication or elsewhere the following quote can be used:
</para>
<para>
<blockquote>
<para>"CloudVeneto is acknowledged for the use of computing and storage facilities."</para>
</blockquote>
</para>
<para>
This technical report can also be used as a reference:
<ulink url="http://paduaresearch.cab.unipd.it/9653/">Progetto CloudVeneto.it - Status Report.</ulink>
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
