<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Users_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="Overview">
<title>Overview of the Cloud Area Padovana</title>
<para>                                                                          
The <literal>Cloud Area Padovana</literal> is an OpenStack based cloud.         
</para>

<para>
It implements a IaaS (Infrastructure as a service):
it allows the instantiations of Virtual Machines (VMs) of the desired
environments (in terms of operating system, installed software, etc.)
and of the desired flavors (in terms of processors, memory size, etc.).
</para>


<para>                                                                          
Even if it is a single, logical Cloud service, its resources are spread in two  
different locations: INFN Padova and INFN Laboratori Nazionali di Legnaro (LNL)\
.                                                                               
</para>

<section id="PreAndProd">
<title>The pre-production and the production services</title>
<para>                                                                          
The Cloud Area Padovana offers a                                                
<literal>pre-production service</literal> based on the Havana version of the    
OpenStack middleware.                                                           
</para>

<para>                                                                          
A <literal>production service</literal> is now being settled: it is also based  
on Openstack Havana version, but it offers improved functionality and           
more resources with respect to the pre-production service.                      
</para>

<para>                                                                          
The preproduction service will be dismissed when the production service         
is fully operational and when all the users have migrated to it.                
</para>

</section>

<section id="Projects">
<title>Projects</title>
<para>
<literal>Projects</literal> (also known as tenants)                             
are organizational units in the cloud. A project is used to map or isolate users 
and their resources. </para>

<para>                                                                             
Projects are given quotas on resource usage, in terms of virtual machines, cores,  
memory, storage, etc.                                                              
</para>

<para>                                                                             
A project can have a single user as member (personal project) but the typical use  
case are shared projects, with multiple users as members, which can map to experim\
ents,                                                                              
organizations, research groups, etc.                                               
A user can be on multiple projects at the same time and switch between them.       
</para>


<para>                                                                             
In the Cloud Area Padovana projects usually map to experiments or other research g\
roups                                                                              
who "own" resources in the cloud service.                                          
Each project has a manager (usually the team leader), who is responsible to manage\
                                                                                   
(accepting or refusing) membership requests for the project.                       
</para>

<para>                                                                             
A special shared project, called <literal>guest</literal> is used for all other    
users: it has a small quota to allow testing the Cloud infrastructure.             
</para>

<para>                                                                             
Personal projects are instead discouraged and are created only for convincing      
reasons.                                                                           
</para>
</section>

<section id="GettingHelp">
<title>Getting help</title>
<para>                                                                             
If you have problems using the Cloud dell'area Padovana private cloud, please 
contact the admins at <email>cloud-support@lists.pd.infn.it</email>.
</para>

<para>                                                                             
Changes and planned interventions to the service will be posted on the             
<email>cloud-users@lists.pd.infn.it</email>.                                       
All registered users to the Cloud are member of this mailing list.    
</para>
</section>

</chapter>
